

ANALYTICS TRAINING SPECIALIST · ADJUNCT PROFESSOR

3419 Superior Park Drive, Cleveland Heights, Ohio, 44118, U.S.

■ ben.bubnick@gmail.com | • bubnicbf | • benbubnick

"10+ years experience physics lecturer with strong academic and teaching background, possessing solid experience managing a wide variety of training programs. Noted history of demonstrating excellent teaching that fosters students' critical skills leading to significantly improved performance. Comfortable within all teaching environments and able to demonstrate a vast range of other transferrable skills and organizational/administrative expertise."

Summary

Professional Summary Data Curation, Data Science, Analytics Training, Machine Learning, Scientific Analysis

Core Competencies Cognitive Practitioner, Metrics Improvement, Agile Development, Training Development

Industries Health Care, Financial & Insurance, Chemicals Manufacturing, R&D/Scientific Research

Demonstrated Past Success Subject Matter Expert, Lab Services Award Winner, Eminence and Excellence Award Winner

I manage client resources and drive technical solutions to timely completion. I identify, analyze, and extract key data from heterogeneous systems; and lead technical requirements gathering, data discovery, documentation, and implementation of assigned client integrations. I also lead technical delivery of assigned client integrations which has included the ordering, installation, and configuration of required hardware, including VPN devices to support client integrations. Configuration and development of software necessary to support client integrations, including ETL and Data Validation.

Experience

AI Data Curation Architect

IBM

WATSON HEALTH Jan. 2018 - PRESENT

Lead member of Data Onboarding & Governance, member of the Watson Foundation for Health Solutions Architecture team. Remediation of data issues during UAT. Builds the data onboarding platform and associated infrastructure, and develop improvements to reducing customer implementation cycle time and data triage activities, and report on the "health of the data" during data onboarding. Tune machine learning classificiation algorithms for patient matching, and the perform the internal review of similar work by my peers.

- Reduced mapping rework by 45% with through new knowledge-driven initiatives
- Developed new data validation and review process that reduced total rework by 25%
- Managed and developed ambitious multi-org enterprise with over 70 interconnected, project-sized components
- Earned AI certification to peer review tuning algorithm and reviewed over 50% of projects in the last 2 quarters
- Earned 7 badges during IBM Re-skilling Initiative and logged over 200 hours of training in 2018
- Curated 25 pages of AI workflow documentation and mentored new hires in AI tuning process
- · Awarded Lab Services Award for coordinating internal project teams to deliver client needs on time
- Awarded GDP bonus for improving revenue per SaaS client by at least 1.34%

Data Scientist IBM, Explorys

WATSON HEALTH, EXPLORYS AN IBM COMPANY

Jun. 2015 - May. 2018

Data Ingestions, pre-analytic enrichments, analytic augmentation, and data governance. Identified and extracted key data from multiple heterogeneous systems; and led technical requirements gathering, data discovery, documentation, and implementation of assigned client integrations. Ordered and oversaw installation of & configuration of required hardware, including VPN devices to support client integrations. Configuration and development of software necessary to support client integrations.

- Eliminated need for a \$30,000 annual contract by developing data curation tool
- Principal integration specialist on over 60 projects for 20 different clients
- Chosen as team lead for ≈12 remote data science contractors for 36 integration projects throughout 2015 2017
- Went above my duties to close project documentation gaps, organizing more than 100 past projects
- Created over 125 new knowledge base articles, making up 30% of the team's online content
- Reduced time spent on knowledge transfer by ≈80% by reorganizing project documentation
- · Awarded Eminence and Excellence Award in 2017 for analytics project
- Awarded GDP bonus for improving revenue per SaaS client by at least 1.17%

Watson Heatlh Sep. 2016 - PRESENT

Project Management for technical training, providing both basic and advanced software training, along with consulting through cross-team and other training/presentation settings. Designed and managed the internal training, an effective onboarding program, and cross-team development training. Focus on HDFS technologies: Pig, Hive & Impala, Ruby & Java.

- Eliminated average of 3 weeks from employee onboarding process
- Reduced cost-per-hire by \$5,210 by re-developing education program
- Spearheaded new-hire mentoring program that led to ≈4,500 increase in total billable hours
- Trained 60% of current data curation teams, including 2 managers

Software Engineer AmTrust Financial Services

COMMERCIAL PACKAGE POLICIES

Mar 2014 - Jun 2015

Developed web forms for insurance industry using ISO standards and created multi-tier MVC components, Web APIs, and UIs using VB, ASP, Javascript, & HTML5

- Development on two software architecture projects in 2015 and principal developer on offering product in 2014
- Developed over 65 ISO rating based web forms for insurance industry
- Collaborated with developers and business analysts to prioritize needs
- Steered development group into a unit testing project on multi-tier MVC components in 2014

Color Scientist PPG Industries PPG Industries

Automotive Refinish Apr. 2012 - Jun. 2013

Developed software and radiative transfer models on complex paint mixtures to determine formulation methods and for spectroscopic profile analysis on color match samples.

- · Improved color matching classification algorithm performance by 40% through new numerical methods
- Wrote and filed application for patent on the application of the Radiative Transfer Equation (Chandrasekhar) to automotive coatings classification models
- Developed cross-instrument correlation software for risk analysis project
- · Awarded Color Lab Automation Award in 2012 for color matching laboratory opening

Adjunct Professor various colleges

LORAIN COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE, MIAMI UNIVERSITY, CINCINNATI STATE TECHNICAL AND COMMUNITY COLLEGE

Aug. 2010 - May. 2019

Developed curricula in introductory physics & astronomy courses, and technical presentations of complex physical concepts for major, non-major, and remedial students. Wrote concise laboratory instruction manuals, trained in precise measurement techniques & data analysis using DataStudio, and coordinated analysis documentation.

- Exceeded feedback evaluation goals by an average of 16% in 2017 and by 17% in 2018
- Tracked a 28% reduction in student confusion by reorganizing online education materials
- Uploaded over 700 hours of pre-recorded lecture material for convenient consumption

Scientific Research University of Cincinati

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS Sep. 2006 - Sep. 2010

Gathered data using SpeX, a $0.8-5.4\,\mu m$ spectrograph, at the NASA Infrared Telescope Facility. Observations in the short-wavelength, crossdispersed mode SXD. Multiple analysis projects comparing 2MASS with measured data, statistical classification without independent photometry for cluster properties, and photometric analysis bootstrapped to independent measurements.

- · Volunteered 120 hours of Quality Control for the Cambridge Astronomical Survey Unit Variable Stars database
- Published 3 scholarly articles on near-infrared astrophysics over a 24-month period
- Awarded Hanna Research Fellowship in 2010

Talks.

IBM Watson Care Insights Reach Initiative

Watson Health

TRAINER

Apr. - Sep. 2018

Watson Care Insights aims to analyze longitudinal patient records and real-time data points through HL7 feeds to provide practitioners insights
into the patient's data. Watson Care Insights seeks to overcome physician-reported challenges incorporating shared decision making technology into their direct patient interactions, and address these challenges by integrating within the physician's workflow in the electronic health
record system.

Content & Data Analytics Learning Exchange

Watson Health

PEER PRESENTER

Apr. & May 2018

- Bayesian Statistics using the Monty Hall problem example
- · Naive Bayesian classification for patient matching
- · Splines regression for population vitals ditributions

2018 IRI Fall Networks Conference

Innovation Research Interchange

Presenter for the Information Services/Information Technology Network Talks

Sep. 2018

• Cognitive computing can use NLP to extract insights from the unstructured data that holds most of the relevant information, but also it can also perform the necessary transformation accurately at the earliest stages of the data integration pipeline. Combined with the scalability and speed of the data lake architecture, this and other cognitive tools can effectively close the gaps on some of the most formidable flat file curation challenges.

Cross Team Training Series

Explorys

LEAD PRESENTER FOR THE METL GROUP

Sep. 2016

• Seven part series in data ingestion approach using the Hadoop software framework. Data can be aggregated much more quickly and cost-effectively using a data lake framework than in traditional data warehouses, because of the speed and low-cost of massively parallel computing. All data is stored in the data lake in its native format until it is needed, and each data element has a metadata tag for easy retrieval. As a result, responses are ad-hoc rather than predetrmined, and reports based on new requirements can be delivered in days or weeks rather than months or years.

Writing

Process and Requirements for CCD Data Integration

IBM

LEAD INTEGRATION DEVELOPER

Oct. 2017

· White paper on processes and requirements overcoming the many difficulties with flat file data curation of CCDs.

Characterization of Surface Coatings using Radiative Transfer Models for Color Matching

PPG

RADIATIVE TRANSFER PHYSICS

Dec. 2010

• Approximation of Chandrasekhar radiative transfer model for atmospheric scattering is applied to color matching. (U.S Patent Application)

Massive Stellar Clusters in the Disk of the Milky Way Galaxy

OhioLINK ETD

GRADUATE RESEARCHER

Dec. 2010

• Using spectroscopic and photometric analysis of two open clusters to determine the structure of the plane of the Milky Way Galaxy.

Near-Infrared Spectroscopy of Candidates Members of the Galactic Cluster [BDS2003] 107

PASP

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Feb. 2008

New near-infrared classification spectra for nine candidate members and comparative 2MASS photometry for several cluster members.

Volunteer

2018/19 Instructor, Computer Science supplemental high school course hosted by BioEnterprise CSforCLE/CMSD
2018/19 Volunteer Coach, Data Science High School Competition hosted by Case Western Reserve University
2015 ETL Volunteer, RTAHeatMap project for Open Cleveland, a Code for America Brigade Open Cleveland
2008/09 Tutor, On-site after school tutoring for T.C.P. World Academy Community School

Education

Master of Science in Physics

University of Cincinnati

McMicken College of Arts and Sciences

2008 - 2010

• Thesis - Massive Stellar Clusters in the Disk of the Milky Way Galaxy

Bachelor of Fine Arts in Printmaking

Ohio University

COLLEGE OF FINE ARTS

2000 - 2004

• Thesis - A Novel Method for Low-Toxic Photo-Etch Printing

Certificate of Specialization in Data Science (MOOC)

Johns Hopkins University

BLOOMBERG SCHOOL OF PUBLIC HEALTH

2015 - 2016

· Capstone - A Machine Learning Algorithm for Paint Formula Prediction from Spectroscopic Measurements

Certifications in Data Science

2019

COGNITIVE CLASS

• Machine Learning with Python - Machine Learning, Regression, Classification, Unsupervised Learning, and Recommender Systems

Badges in Data Science

IBM 2018

COGNITIVE CLASS

Cognitive Practitioner - Foundational understanding of IBM Cognitive solutions and offerings

Hadoop Data Access - Hive and Hive QL data access on Hadoop

Badges in Software Architecture

IBM

Infrastucture & Architecture

2018

IBM Cloud Private - Architecture and infrastructure requirements for deploying microservices-based cloud native applications

· Blockchain Essentials - Blockchain principles & practices, Distributed ledger systems, and asset transfer

Badges in Business IBM

OFFERING MANAGEMENT 2018 • Offering Manager: Scaling the Business - Scale a business through Digital Channels, Expansive Ecosystems, and Value-based Service Delivery

- Offering Manager: Manage the Business Holistic view of Health of Business and Customer Sentiment
- Offering Manager: Define, Build & Deliver Offering Launch/Delivery (OD) discipline for delivering an offering to market

Badge in Agile Development AGILE DEVELOPMENT

2017

IBM

• Agile Explorer - Foundational understanding of Agile values, principles, and practices